Register of the Charles Hill Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Charles Hill papers
1898-2006
89004
Hoover Institution Archives
157 manuscript boxes, 6 oversize boxes, 9 card file boxes, 1 cubic foot box, 2 envelopes (70.9 linear feet)
Collection includes correspondence, speeches and writings, dispatches, memoranda, reports, notes, printed matter, memorabilia, and photographs relating to international relations and diplomacy, American foreign policy during the presidential administration of Ronald Reagan, and the Chinese Cultural Revolution. Also contains speeches and writings of Secretary of State George Shultz. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Hill, Charles, 1936-
Access
Boxes 39-51 closed. The remainder of the collection is open for research. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives between 1989 and 2011.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1936, April 28 Born, Bridgeton, New Jersey
1957 A.B., Brown University
1960 J.D., University of Pennsylvania
1961 M.A., University of Pennsylvania
1963 Vice Consul, Zurich
1964 Chinese Language Officer, Taichung, Taiwan
1966-1969 Political Officer, Hong Kong
1970 Fellow, East Asia Center, Harvard University
1971 Author, The Cultural Revolution in the Provinces
1971-1973 Mission Coordinator, American Embassy, Saigon, Vietnam
1974 Policy Planning Staff, Department of State
1978 Deputy Director, Israel Desk, Department of State
1979 Political Counselor, American Embassy, Tel Aviv, Israel
1981 Director, Israel and Arab-Israeli Affairs, Department of State
1982 Deputy Assistant Secretary of State, Middle East
1983 Executive Secretary, Department of State
1984-1989 Executive Assistant to the Secretary of State
1989-1992 Diplomat-in-Residence, Stanford University
1989- Senior Research Fellow, Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace
1992- Diplomat-in-Residence and Lecturer in International Studies and Directed Studies, Yale University
1992-1996 Special Advisor to Secretary-General Boutros Boutros-Ghali, United Nations
Scope and Content of Collection
Collection includes correspondence, speeches and writings, dispatches, memoranda, reports, notes, printed matter, memorabilia, and photographs relating to international relations and diplomacy, American foreign policy during the presidential administration of Ronald Reagan, and the Chinese Cultural Revolution. Also contains speeches and writings of Secretary of State George Shultz.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into series: Biographical File, Correspondence, Speeches and Writings, Subject File, Oversize File, Card File, Stanford Years File, Increments, and Declassified government records.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
China--History--Cultural Revolution, 1966-1976.; Diplomats--United States.; International relations.; Reagan, Ronald.; Shultz, George Pratt, 1920-.; United States--Foreign relations--1981-1989.; United States. Dept. of State.
- Biographical File, 1978-1988. (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Career records and biographical data related to Charles Hill's government service, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Biographical sketches
  - Career, personal files
  - Clippings
  - Telephone numbers
- Correspondence, 1978-1987. (Box 2)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - General, 1978-1987
  - Abrams, Elliott, 1986
  - Bunker, Ellsworth, 1979
  - Castle, Peter, ca. 1986
  - Edelman, Eric, 1987
  - Haig, Alexander, 1984
  - Kissinger, Henry, 1985-1986
  - LaFeber, Walter, 1983-1986 (Box 3)
  - Levy, Arnold, 1982-1987
  - Lord, Winston, 1987
  - Nixon, Richard, 1985
  - Quinn, Kenneth, 1981-1982
  - Rafael, Gideon, 1981-1987
  - Reagan, Ronald, 1982
  - Roberts, Sam, 1986-1987
  - Seitz, R. H. G., 1984
  - Shultz, George, 1985
  - Sofaer, Abraham, 1986
- Speeches and Writings, 1968-1986.
  Notes, drafts, research materials arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Handwritten notes, including notes on China, 1968-1970
    drafts
  - Research materials
- Subject File, 1942-1989.
  Memoranda, correspondence, charts, maps, outlines, dispatches, reports, press summaries, printed matter, arranged alphabetically by subject. Includes notes and speeches by Charles Hill
  - ABM/SDI (Anti-Ballistic Missiles/Strategic Defense Initiative). Printed matter, 1988
  - Abrams, Elliott. Correspondence, interview, printed matter, 1987-1988
  - Adams family. Memorandum and chronology of Adams family, beginning with President John Adams (1735-1826), 1985
  - Afghanistan. Printed matter, 1988
  - Africa. Printed matter, 1988
  - African Americans.
    General note
    See Black Americans
  - Anthropology. "Stakes in Anthropology" by Ernest Gellner, American Scholar, undated
  - Anti-communism. "Liberal Anti-Communism Revisited" from We Must March My Darlings by Diana Trilling, 1977
  - Arafat, Yasser. Correspondence, memorandum, United Nations draft resolution, printed matter, 1988
  - Arendt, Hannah. "Thinking," New Yorker, November, 1977
  - Aristotle. "On the Early History of the Aristotelian Corpus" by Carnes Lord, American Journal of Philology, 1986
  - Arms control. Correspondence, memorandum, printed matter, 1987-1989 (Box 4)
  - Arms race. Charts, 1982-1987; printed matter, undated
  - Aron, Raymond. "Raymond Aron" by Edward Shils, American Scholar, undated
  - Atomic power. Excerpt from Atomic Quest by Arthur Holly Compton, "Landing in the New World," 1956; map of the University of Chicago, undated
  - Australia. "Political Ideology in Australia: The Distinctiveness of a Benthamite Society" by Hugh Collins, Daedalus, Winter 1985
  - Bach, Johann S. "When God Shared J.S. Bach" by William F. Buckley, Jr., 1985
  - Baker, James, III. Biographical printed matter, 1989
  - Bakhtin, Mikhail. "Readying Bakhtin" by Denis Donoghue, Raritan, undated
  - Basketball. Printed matter, 1988
  - Bechtel. Editorial on "Friends in High Places" by Laton McCartney, 1988
  - Bellow, Saul. Interviews, 1984
  - Black Americans. "Black Americans and International Affairs," speech by Maureen Bunyan, February 4, 1986
  - Bloom, Allan. Reviews, 1987
  - Books. Book lists, bookstores
  - Bork, Robert. Correspondence (George Shultz to Robert Dole), 1987
  - Bunker, Ellsworth. Correspondence, obituaries, printed matter, 1984-1987
  - Bureaucracy. "Bureaucracy Baiting" by Stephen Miller, American Scholar, undated
  - Bush, George, and the Bush Administration. Speeches, printed matter, 1988
  - Capitalism. "Is There a Moral Basis for Capitalism?" by Paul Johnson, undated
  - Carr, J. L. Book review, undated
  - Carter, Jimmy. Remarks at Ecumenical Prayer Service, Lincoln Memorial, undated
  - Cartoons
  - Central America.
    Outlines, notes, memoranda, printed matter, 1985-1988; including memorandum to Robert McFarlane, January 18, 1985, on Decision to Withdraw from the International Court of Justice Case, with background material attached
  - Chambers, Whittaker. Sidney Hook letter to the editor of New Criterion, relating to Witness, September 1988
  - Change. "Pace of Change" presented before the American Statistical Association, December 27, 1970
  - Chevening.
    Printed matter on the Chevening estate in Kent, England
  - Child abuse. Book review of Children at Risk: My Fight Against Child Abuse, by Senator Paula Hawkins, undated
  - Chile. Article from New York Times, October 4, 1988
  - China (Box 5)
    - General
      - Printed matter in Chinese and English, notes
      - Charts, maps (Box 6)
      - Poster of Mao Tse-tung
      - Printed matter
    - Cultural Revolution (Box 7)
      - General
        - General
        - Notes
        - Telegrams, January-June 1967
      - British Charge, Peking. Dispatches, reports (Box 8)
        See also Declassified government records
      - 1966 December
      - 1967
        - January-February
        - March-May (Box 9)
        - December
      - Lu Hsun, Reports on
      - Red Guards (Box 10)
      - United Action Committee
    - Foreign relations
      - Soviet Union
      - Taiwan
      - Miscellany
    - Politics and government
      - Government and Communist Party officials, 1968
      - Peking Consular officials, 1950
  - Christian-Islamic confrontation. "Christian-Islamic Confrontation in the West: The Thirteenth-Century Dream of Conversion" by Robert I. Burns, American Historical Review, December 1971 (Box 11)
  - Churchill, Winston. Book review of Finest Hour by Martin Gilbert, New Republic, December 5, 1983
  - Classics. Review of Greek Experience by C. M. Bowra in The Times, June 8-14, 1985
  - Clifford, Clark. Correspondence, 1986; speeches, 1976-1984
  - Cold War
    - Memorandum
    - "American Conception of National Security and the Beginnings of the Cold War, 1945-48" by Melvyn P. Leffler, AHR Forum, undated
    - "Beyond the Cold War" by Charles Krauthammer, New Republic, December 19, 1988
    - "Economic Security and the Origins of the Cold War: Bretton Woods, the Marshall Plan, and Rearmament, 1944-50" by Robert A. Pollard, Diplomatic History
  - Committee of Concerned Asian Scholars. Newsletter, September, November 1970
  - Communism - Europe. Printed matter, 1988
  - Compassion. "Compassion" by Clifford Orwin, American Scholar, undated
  - Congo. Correspondence, report, 1962
  - Council on Foreign Relations. Printed matter, 1985
  - Covert operations. Printed matter, 1988
  - Crane, Stephen. Book review, July 1988
  - Crew racing. Printed matter, 1985
  - Cuba. Notes, reports, printed matter, 1962, 1982
  - Cultural policy. Notes, correspondence (Alistair Cooke to George Shultz), February 25, 1985
  - Darwin, Charles
    - "Darwinian Revolution and Literary Form" by A. Dwight Fuller
    - "Darwin's Vision in On the Origin of Species by Walter F. Cannon, undated
  - Debt - Third World. Printed matter, 1989
  - Defense
    - Speech by Colin L. Powell, 1988 Air Force Association Convention, September 19, 1988
    - "Deterrence: The Problem-Not the Solution" by Michael McGwire, 1986
    - "What Ever Happened to the Nixon Doctrine?" by Samuel T. Cohen, Policy Review, Fall 1983
  - Deficit. Memorandum, "When to Worry About the Deficit" by John H. Makin, AEI Economist, November 6, 1984
  - Democracy
    - "Can the Democracies Survive?" by Jean-Francois Revel, Commentary, June 1984
    - "I Speak for Democracy" by Elizabeth Ellen Evans, Voice of Firestone (radio and television), 1954
    - "Tocqueville Revisited: Are Good Democracies Bad Players in the Game of Nations?" by Josef Joffe, Washington Quarterly, Winter 1988
    - "Tocqueville's Challenge" by David Clinton, Washington Quarterly, Winter 1988
  - Diplomacy
    - "Diplomacy in an Election Year and Beyond," speech by Max Kampelman, Georgetown University School of Foreign Service, October 7, 1988
    - "Diplomacy Is All in a Day's Work" by Barbara Gamarekian, New York Times, March 5, 1987
    - "Diplomacy of Small Countries" by Adamantios Th. Vassilakis, Bohemian Club Library Notes, Spring 1988
    - "Future of the World: Diplomatic Challenge and Change in the Coming Century," book outline, memorandum, February 22, 1989
    - Introduction, Foundations of American Diplomacy, 1775-1872 by Robert H. Ferrell, undated
    - "Lessons in Diplomacy" by Martin F. Herz, Foreign Service Journal, October 1982
    - "Notes on the Management of Multilateral Diplomacy" by Otho E. Eskin, 1977
    - "Our Faltering Diplomacy" by Smith Simpson, Foreign Service Journal, September 1983
    - "Potemkin Palace" by Daniel Patrick Moynihan, National Interest, Winter 1986 (Box 12)
    - "Public Diplomacy: Challenge and Response," Washington Quarterly, October 30, 1985
    - "Summits of Yore: Promises and a Deal or Two" by Robert Wernick, undated
    - Miscellaneous printed matter, 1986, 1988
  - Dolan, Anthony R. Resume
  - Eastern Europe. "Czechoslovakia 1938-Israel 1980" by Steven Plaut, Commentary, August 1980; printed matter, 1988
  - Eban, Abba. "Central Question," Tikkun, undated
  - Economics
    - "Economics and the National Security" by Murray Weidenbaum, Washington Quarterly, Autumn 1988
    - "Economics as a System of Belief,", undated
    - "On Schelling, Hirschman, and Sen: Revising the Conception of the Self" by Michael McPherson, Partisan Review, 1982
    - "Quest for a Durable Global Monetary System,", undated
  - Editing. "Behind the Blue Pencil" by Jacques Barzun, undated
  - Education
    - "The Business of Education," book review, American Scholar, undated
    - "Design for a New Academy" by Frederick Turner, Harper's, undated
    - "Education as Recollection, Encounter and Ascent" by David J. Levy, World and I, undated
    - "Louis Hartz's Teaching," by Paul Roazen, Virginia Quarterly Review, undated
    - "Watching the Pendulum in Education" by Vermont Royster, American Scholar, undated
  - Emerson, Ralph W. "Emerson and the Essay" by William H. Gass, Yale Review, undated
  - Espionage. Printed matter, 1986-1987
  - Europe. "Economic Sluggishness of Western Europe" by Arthur Burns, 1984; printed matter, 1984-1988
  - Executives. Note, printed matter, undated
  - Farrell, James T. "Echoes of Lonigan, 50 Years After" by Samuel G. Freedman, undated
  - Foote, Shelby. "Shelby Foote's Iliad" by Helen White and Redding S. Sugg, Jr., Georgia Review, undated
  - Foreign policy. "Reading by Cuisinart" by Henry Allen, undated
  - Foreign service. Correspondence, speeches by Ronald I. Spiers, 1985-1988; reports, printed matter, 1977-1988
  - France - Diplomacy. Correspondence, report, 1984
  - Franklin, Benjamin. "Dr. Franklin: Friend of the Indians" by Julian P. Boyd, Journal of the Franklin Institute, October 1942
  - Friedman, Milton and Rose. "Tide in the Affairs of Men,", undated
  - Gaddis, John. "Containment and the Logic of Strategy," National Interest, Winter 1987-1988
  - Gelb, Leslie. Copy of George Shultz letter to Dante Fascell on press leaks, March 25, 1985
  - Geneva Accords. Text, April 1988
  - Germany. Treaties, etc. - Soviet Union, 1939 August 31. "The Nazi-Soviet Pact: Missing Page in Soviet Historiography" by Vladimir Petrov, 1968
  - Gibson, Andrew E. Resume
  - Global interdependence. "Twilight of Autarchy" by Lincoln P. Bloomfield, Harvard Magazine, undated
  - Golding, William. "'Stranger From Within' into 'Lord of the Flies'," Times Literary Supplement, September 1986
  - Gorbachev, Mikhail. "Djilas on Gorbachov," Milovan Djilas and George Urban in conversation, 1988; printed matter, 1987-1988
  - Great Britain
    - General. Printed matter, 1981-1985
    - Foreign relations – Soviet Union. "Watching the 'Steamroller': British Observers and the Russian Army Before 1914" by K. Nielson, undated
  - Harvard E. Asian Research Center. Directories, 1969, 1970 (Box 13)
  - Harvard Negotiation Project. Memorandum, report, 1987
  - Hayes, Woody. "A Tribute to Woody Hayes," remarks by Richard Nixon, March 1987
  - Helms, Jesse. Printed matter, 1988
  - Herodotus
    - "Narrative Surface and Authorial Voice in Herodotus' Histories" by Carolyn Dewald, Arethusa, 1987
    - "Persians, Greeks and Empire" by David Konstan, Arethusa, 1987
  - Herzog, Chaim. Speech at the conferment of an honorary degree, Georgetown University, November 22, 1983
  - Hill, Martha. "Innovations of Martha Hill," Dance View, New York Times, March 1982
  - History and historians
    - "A Historian as Museum Curator" by Alfred Young, Perspectives, October 1988
    - "Some Characteristics of Historians in Democratic Times,", undated
    - "Some Models Used by Intellectual Historians" by Roland N. Stromberg, undated
    - "Why Study History?" by Paul Gagnon, Atlantic Monthly, November 1988
  - Hong Kong. List of correspondents, media services, and regional magazines, April 15, 1969
  - Hook, Sidney
    - "Case of Alger Hiss," American Chronicle, undated
    - "Lillian Hellman's Scoundrel Time," Authors and Critics, undated
    - "A Philosophical Perspective,", undated
    - "Sidney Hook, Embattled Philosopher" by Nathan Glick, Encounter, June 1985
  - Hostages. Printed matter, 1988
  - Human rights. Correspondence, testimony, report, printed matter, 1983-1988
  - Human studies. Printed matter, 1986
  - India
    - "An Indian Dynasty: Story of the Nehru-Gandhi Family" by T. Ali, New Republic, May 27, 1985
    - "Rising Regional Powers," Center for the Study of Foreign Affairs Bulletin, November 1988
  - Indians. "Indian Affairs in Pennsylvania, 1736-1762,", undated
  - Indochina. "Department of Disinformation: The Lessons of Indochina," Policy Review, Spring 1985
  - Industrial Workers of the World (I.W.W.). Printed matter, 1984 (Box 14)
  - Information age. Correspondence, speech, printed matter, 1987-1988
  - Institute of Pacific Relations. "The Institute of Pacific Relations and the Origins of Asian and Pacific Studies" by Paul Hooper, Pacific Affairs, Spring 1988
  - Intermediate-range Nuclear Forces (I.N.F.). "START: A Good Agreement for the US" by Paul Nitze; printed matter, 1988
  - International law
    - "Challenging Covert War: The Politics of the Political Question Doctrine" by David Cole, Harvard International Law Journal, Winter 1985
    - "Classics of International Law," part of a book by Samuel von Pufendorf, undated
    - "How to Rescue International Law" by Gidon Gottlieb, Commentary, October 1984
    - "International Law and International Lies" by I. Kristol, Wall Street Journal, June 21, 1985
    - "International Law, the Reagan Doctrine, and World Peace: Going Back to the Future" by Robert F. Turner, Washington Quarterly, Autumn 1988
  - International relations
    - Notes
    - "Crisis Decision Making: The Banality of Theory" by Adam M. Garfinkle, Orbis, Spring 1986
    - "First World War and the International Power System" by Paul M. Kennedy, International Security, Summer 1984
    - "Foreign Affairs: A Budget Pariah" by David Newsom, Christian Science Monitor, November 8, 1987
    - "From Illusions to Norms in International Relations" by Kenneth W. Thompson, Society, November/December 1987
    - "Ideology in International Politics," Jerusalem Journal of International Relations, March 1987
    - "Influence of Geopolitics on the East-West Struggle" by Michael Howard, Parameters, September 1988
    - "Jet Planes, Television, and Foreign Policy" by George W. Ball, SAIS Review, Winter 1981
    - "Leashing the Dogs of War" by David S. Broder, n.d
    - "Multipolarity in World Politics" by Norman A. Graebner, Virginia Quarterly Review, Summer 1988
    - "Neorealism and Neoliberalism" by Joseph S. Nye, Jr., World Politics, January 1988
    - "'Operational Code'" by Alexander L. George, International Studies Quarterly, June 1960
    - "Strategy, Diplomacy, and the Cold War: The United States, Turkey, and N.A.T.O., 1945-52" by Melvyn P. Leffler, undated
    - "Stung by the Reagan Doctrine?" Washington Times, April 13, 1988
    - "Three Concepts of Internationalism" by Fred Halliday, lecture given at the London School of Economics, 1987
  - Iran-Contra Affair, 1985-1990
    - "Boland Specter" by Paul Greenberg, May 27, 1987
    - "Committee That Couldn't Shoot Straight" by Steven Waldman, Washington Monthly, September 1988
    - "Journal in Turmoil" by Sidney Blumenthal, Washington Post, February 16, 1987
  - Islam. "Islam and the Revolt of the Petite Bourgeoisie" by Michael M. J. Fischer, undated
  - Israel. Correspondence, report, speech, printed matter, 1977-1988.
    Including Joe Sisco's "Aide-memoire"
  - Japan. "Japan After American Hegemony" by Ezra F. Vogel for the U.S. State Department, January 1986, draft; printed matter, 1988 (Box 15)
  - Judaism. Outline on Judaism; printed matter, undated
  - Kennan, George
    - "George Kennan vs. Mr. 'X'" by Paul Seabury, New Republic, December 16, 1981
    - "Strange Case of George F. Kennan: From Containment to Isolationism" by Edward N. Luttwak, Commentary, November 1977
    - "Learning to Live Without a Soviet Threat." Interview, original in New Perspectives Quarterly, undated
    - "Two Views of the Soviet Problem" by George Kennan, New Yorker, undated
  - Keynes, John Maynard. "General Keynes" by John Kenneth Galbraith, New York Review of Books, undated
  - Kissinger, Henry
    - Memorandum, James P. Timbie to Secretary of State George Shultz, June 14, 1988
    - "America and the World: Principle and Pragmatism," Time, December 27, 1976
    - "Challenge of a 'European Home',", undated
    - "International Economics and World Order," First Annual Mocatta Lecture, September 24, 1984
    - "International Trade: It's Time to Change the Rules,", October 22, 1984
    - "Issues Before the Atlantic Alliance," The Future of NATO and Global Security Conference, Georgetown University, January 13, 1984
    - "A Memo to the Next President," Newsweek, September 19, 1988
    - "Observations on U.S.-Soviet Relations," Heritage Foundation, January 14, 1988
    - "START: A Dangerous Rush for Agreement," Los Angeles Times, 1988
    - "Diplomacy of Henry Kissinger" by Theodore Draper, Dissent, Spring 1980
    - "Interface Between Beliefs and Behavior: Henry Kissinger's Operational Code and the Vietnam War" by Stephen G. Walker, Journal of Conflict Resolution, March 1977
    - "Kissinger Reconsidered" by Norman Podhoretz, Commentary, June 1982
    - "Vermeer, Aristotle, Nero, Seneca, Kissinger" by Andre de Staercke, undated
  - LaFeber, Walter
    - "Decline of the Postwar Relationship: The United States and Japan During the Vietnam War, 1960-1975,", undated
    - "Inevitable Revolutions," Atlantic Monthly, June 1982
    - "Last War, Next War and New Revisionists,", 1981
    - "Third Cold War," Charles Edmondson Historical Lecture, Baylor University, January 14/15, 1980
    - "Under the Volcano." Review of Inevitable Revolutions by Bernard Aronson, New Republic, February 6, 1984
  - Language. Memorandum, printed matter, 1982-1987
  - Latin America
    - "Challenge of Ideology in Latin America" by Richard M. Morse, AEI Foreign Policy and Defense Review, undated
    - "Future of Latin America: Any Cause for Optimism?" AEI Foreign Policy and Defense Review, undated
    - "Intervention in Latin America: Cuba Si, Yanqui No'?" speech by Elliott Abrams, April 18, 1986
  - Leaking (press leaks). Copies of memoranda, 1986; printed matter; talking points for George Shultz.
    See also Gelb, Leslie
  - Libya. Printed matter, January 1989
  - Literature and literary criticism
    - "Canonical and Non-Canonical: A Critique of the Current Debate" by John Guillory, undated
    - "From Imitation to Rhetoric: The Chicago Critics, Wayne C. Booth, and Tom Jones" by John Ross Baker, Novel, Spring 1973
    - "Liars and Truth-Tellers, Fancy and Plain" by Peter Stitt, Georgia Review, undated
    - "Literature and Technology" by Cleanth Brooks, undated
    - "Poaching Off the Disciplines" by Bruce Robbins, Raritan, undated
    - "Shooting the Literary Rapids" by Pat Rogers, Times Literary Supplement, November 15, 1985